Guide to the Stanford University, Committee on Land and Building Development, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Stanford University, Committee on Land and Building Development, records
1950-1990
SC0813
Stanford University. Committee on Land and Building Development
1.5 Linear feet (3 boxes)
The collection primarily contains minutes, with some correspondence and reports. Occasionally the minutes include supporting documents relevant to the business discussed and minutes from the sub-committee on faculty/staff housing are often included. Specific projects covered in these records include the VA hospital, the Palo Alto Hospital, the Pine Hill Subdivision, the fraternity clusters project, additions to the Stanford Linear Accelerator (SLAC), plans for the Cowell Student Health Center, and the Peter Coutts faculty housing project.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Information about Access
This collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 48 hours in advance of intended use.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The Committee on Land and Building Development is responsible for providing input and/or recommendations to the President and other administrative officers on the planning and development of academic campus lands; on basic design guidelines for architecture and landscaping; and planning for transportation services. Committee members include faculty, staff and students representatives.
Description of the Collection
The collection primarily contains minutes, with some correspondence and reports. Occasionally the minutes include supporting documents relevant to the business discussed and minutes from the sub-committee on faculty/staff housing are often included. The records date from 1950 to 1990, but records from the 1960s only cover the years 1963-1966.
In the 1950s the Committee was particularly active in allocating Stanford land for new construction. The major projects undertaken by the committee in this period include the VA hospital, the Palo Alto Hospital and the Pine Hill Subdivision. A reoccurring issue with the committee was the leasing of land, and what the stipulations for payment and accountability would be.
Business before the committee in the 1960s included the fraternity cluster project, additions to the Stanford Linear Accelerator (SLAC), plans for the Cowell Student Health Center, and assigning parcels of land for future sub-divisions.
In the 1970s the committee was especially concerned with providing low/moderate income housing for Stanford faculty and their families. The Peter Coutts Project was the focus of much of their energies. Economic feasibility, house size and ensuring that the elementary schools could support the resident population were just a few of the issues that the committee considered during their deliberations. Another residential area that was developed during this time was Escondido Village. In 1976 the committee reviewed the proposal for the Positron Electron Project, a $78 million dollar project that would expand the already existing Stanford linear accelerator.
The meeting minutes for the later years of the Land and Building Development Committee show that the construction on and around campus slowed dramatically. During the second half of the 1980s the committee was mainly concerned with the upkeep and improvement of existing structures on campus. Parking and adequate lighting along footpaths were the most common improvements undertaken during this period. However, plans for an 8500 square foot child center were passed, as well as a proposal for the Green Earth Sciences Building.
Overall, many of the committee's decisions were concerned with allowing campus growth while maintaining many of principles and ideas that the university was founded upon. For example, in the 1980s the committee designed the Cardinal Plaza, located on the corner of Sam MacDonald and Eucalyptus Roads. It was designed as a place for tailgating, picnics, meetings, and fundraising events. The original plan was defeated by a vote of 3 to 2 because the committee felt that the design, which emphasized extensive brickwork, clashed with the historic "farm" feel of the campus that the committee sought to preserve. Later the plans were redrawn so that the plaza embodied the "farm" feel that Stanford is known for and was approved by the committee.
Access Terms
Stanford Linear Accelerator Center; Stanford University. Committee on Land and Building Development; Campus planning--California--Stanford; Land use--California--Stanford
Collection Contents
- Advisory Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes and correspondence, 1950-52, and reports and studies, 1952-53 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes and correspondence, 1952-1954 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1954-1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Land and Building Development, correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Land and Development, minutes, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Land and Development, minutes, 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1963-1966 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1970 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1970 May-Oct 8 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1970 Oct 15-Dec (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1974 Jan-Apr (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1974 May-Nov (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1976-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Committee on Land and Building Development, minutes, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 9)